<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Thomas Church in Bristol, September 3, 1685 before the Right Honorable the Lord Arthur Somerset, and the Society of the Loyal Young Men and Apprentices of Bristol, at the time of their anniversary feast / by Richard Roberts ...</title>
            <author>Roberts, Richard, fl. 1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16016398</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16016398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Thomas Church in Bristol, September 3, 1685 before the Right Honorable the Lord Arthur Somerset, and the Society of the Loyal Young Men and Apprentices of Bristol, at the time of their anniversary feast / by Richard Roberts ...</title>
                  <author>Roberts, Richard, fl. 1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, II, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Thomas</hi> Church in <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> 3. 1685.</p>
            <p>Before the Right Honorable the Lord ARTHUR Somerſet, AND THE Society of the Loyal Young Men and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> at the time of their Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Feaſt.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>RICHARD ROBERTS,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and Vicar of <hi>All Saints</hi> in <hi>Briſtol,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> at the Golden Ball over againſt the Royal <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex Aedib. Lamb. <date>Oct. 23. 1685.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Needham RR. in Chriſto P. &amp; D. D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honorable the Lord <hi>Arthur Somerſet,</hi> Second Son to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Beaufort.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have often obſerved, that the more ſollicitous ſome perſons appear in framing Apologies for the Publication of their Diſcourſes, the more obnoxious they uſually render themſelves to the Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious laſhes of Captious and Critical Readers. And therefore inſtead of ſtuffing this Epiſtle with formal pretences and excuſes, I think it much fitter to take this opportunity of acquainting the world, that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips great Condeſcenſion in vouchſafing the Loyal Young Men of <hi>Briſtol</hi> the Honor of being their Leader, is not only acknowledged by them with all the dutiful expreſſions of an humble gratitude, but moreover is likely to have a very good influence upon them in order to the Kings Service.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:3"/>
            <p>This perhaps ſome may think meanly and ſlightly of, becauſe the perſons Liſted under your Lordſhips Conduct are for the moſt part in their Minority, and not very many of them are yet arrived to the age and perfection of Men. But they who would have them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued and diſregarded for that reaſon, proceed upon very impolitick grounds, and ſuch as have always proved highly prejudicial to the intereſts of theſe Kingdoms. For, if things be duly weighed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, for that very reaſon becauſe they are Young, the greater countenance and encouragement ought in Policy to be ſhewn unto them, that ſo, when the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of a few years ſhall fix them in the Stations of their Fathers and Maſters, the impreſſions now made upon them may ſhew forth themſelves in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py effects of an active and ſteady Loyalty. Had this conſideration been had, and the thing rightly managed in the Laſt Age, according to the natural conſequences of it, it could not but have fared infinitely better than it hath done in This; for indeed the multitude of turbulent and ungovernable Men, which have now been diſturbing the common peace and tranquillity, is a certain indication of the little care that was then taken of Boys.</p>
            <p>Thus much, My Lord, I thought my ſelf in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice obliged to ſay in Honor of your Lordſhips ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Condeſcenſion. To which, did I imagine it at
<pb facs="tcp:104774:3"/> this time proper, I might at leaſt attempt to ſubjoin a larger Panegyrick upon your Lordſhip, the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of your Deſcent, the extraordinary acuteneſs of your Natural Parts, and the many admirable accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments which by means of an excellent Education you have acquired, affording ample matter for it. But becauſe, notwithſtanding the eminent conſpicuity of theſe things in themſelves, yet the repreſentation of them to your Lordſhip may be adjudged Flattery, I ſhall at preſent forbear the inſiſting any farther on them, only deſiring the favor of humbly remembring your Lordſhip, that the beſt and moſt ingenuous way of improving thoſe advantages and endowments, is to make them always ſubſervient to the Glory of him, who originally gave them unto you. By the doing this, My Lord, you will take the moſt effectual method for the advancing your own Glory, and for the making all the world ſenſible that you Act like a Son of the Great Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Beaufort;</hi> and therefore that you may not fail of endeavouring and obtaining it, ſhall be ever the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt obedient and dutiful Servant, Richard Roberts.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104774:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104774:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SERMON ON 1 Pet. ii. 17. The latter part.</hi>—Honor the King.</head>
            <p>MY deſign in ſpeaking to theſe words at this time is, partly to applaud that excellent Choice, which you the Loyal Young Men of this City made, when even in the blackeſt of times you openly bid defiance to every thing that called it ſelf Seditious or Fanatical, and ſolemnly Devoted your Lives and Fortunes to the Royal Intereſts; and partly to direct your forward Zeal to ſome apt and ſuitable preſſions thereof, that ſo you may not only be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, but may in all inſtances approve your ſelves, what the great reaſon and intent of this Anniverſary Feaſt oblige you all to be.</p>
            <p>In proſecution of which ends, without any farther Introduction, I ſhall make it my buſineſs to repreſent unto you,</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104774:5"/>
               <item>I. What great Obligations there are lying on all Subjects to <hi>Honor the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. What are the moſt proper and effectual Methods for the expreſſing that Honor by;</item>
               <item>II. How unreaſonably ſome men pretend to Honor him, when their practices run counter to his Intereſt concluding all</item>
               <item>IV. With ſome ſeaſonable Improvement of the whole.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. What great Obligations there are lying on all Subjects to Honor the King. And thoſe I take to be principally three, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The expreſs command of God; 2. The ties of common Gratitude; 3. The dictates of common Prudence.</p>
            <p>1. The expreſs command of God. For maugre all the artifices and pretenſions, which the filthy <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi> of old made uſe of for the diſengaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the obligations of Chriſtian ſubjection; maugre all the fallacious Arguments and Apologies, which the Modern <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> of theſe latter Ages have found out for the defence and vindication of their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous and Anti-Chriſtian Practices, yet if there be any credit to be repoſed in the Holy Scriptures, thoſe Lively Oracles of God, there is no truth more certain and undeniable, than that Kings, as they are Kings, have a juſt Right to our profoundeſt reverences and reſpects, and that there is nothing in the whole world ſufficient to annul or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104774:5"/> the indiſpenſable duty of Honour which is owing them. Of this our Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> among the other Sacred Penmen, is a clear and poſitive, as well as infallible, Witneſs. For whereas it was urged in his time, that all the Proſelytes of the Holy Jeſus were the Lords Freemen, that he had delivered them from the ſlavery of Obedience to Magiſtrates who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Tyrannically inſulted over them, and that now they were all become Kings and Princes themſelves, abſolute and independent; our Apoſtle a little before my Text reflects upon the groſneſs and carnality of this their error, telling them indeed that they ought to look upon and value themſelves as Free, <hi>i. e.</hi> as men deliver'd by Chriſt from the Bondage of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial and Judicial Laws; but yet, this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it would be no ways excuſable in them, if they made this Freedom or Deliverance <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a Cloak or Covering for Sedition or any other Wickedneſs. And whereas it is even at this day urged, by ſome in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> on the one hand, that there is no Deference or Allegiance owing to an Heretical Prince; and by moſt of the Puritanical Separatiſts on the other, that there is none owing to a Papiſt Prince, it is remarkable, that <note n="*" place="margin">Tiber. Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, <hi>whoſe Life ſee in</hi> Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> the King, who Reigned, when the Apoſtle wrote this Epiſtle, was an Idolatrous Heathen, and not only ſo, but likewiſe a moſt extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagantly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104774:6"/> debauched and bloody Tyrant. And yet ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Honor the King;</hi> tho the way of Worſhip, which he maintaineth and defendeth, be certainly of all others the moſt vile and abominable, and tho the whole courſe of his Actions be very much beneath the Dignity of a Man, and much more of a Prince; yet ſince the Great Lord and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietary of all things hath thought fit to make him partake of the Glory of the Divinity, by advancing him into the number of the <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. lxxxii. 6.</note> Mortal Gods, you are neceſſarily bound for the ſake of his Eminent Character to deport your ſelves with all dutiful reſpect towards him, leſt otherwiſe by deſpiſing him ye be found deſpiſers of the Almighty <hi>Jehova,</hi> who hath intruſted the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Authority and Juriſdiction in his hands. But,</p>
            <p>2. Another Obligation, which lieth upon all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to Honor the King, is deduced from the ties of common Gratitude. For unleſs a King be mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly negligent or ſavage in the exerciſe of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power, unleſs he totally addicteth himſelf to the brutiſh ſenſualities of the Fleſh, or the more brutiſh efforts of violence and raging Cruelty, the fatigues and cares, which he muſt neceſſarily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo in the Adminiſtration of the Government, cannot but deſerve ſo well at leaſt of the generality of his people, as to derive upon him a very firm Title to the moſt humble expreſſions of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104774:6"/> But, whaever the circumſtances of Forein Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are, I am ſure we of this Nation muſt be moſt horribly ungrateful, and therefore unchriſtian, if we are defective in rendring the due acknowledgments of Honor and Praiſe unto our moſt Excellent Prince. For, if we conſider him in himſelf, his unbiaſſed Juſtice, his exemplary Temperance, his reſolute Courage, his ſagacious Prudence, his never-failing Veracity, his indefatigable Induſtry; together with many other Noble and Godlike Diſpoſitions of Mind: would all exact of us, even if he were not a Prince, a very extraordinary admiration and eſteem. But then, If we conſider him farther as the Man, whom God himſelf hath in a very wounderful manner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to Honor; and that not only in common with other Sovereign Princes, by making him one of his Deputies or Vicegerents here on Earth, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by many miraculous Interpoſitions of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for his ſafety and deliverance, by reſcuing him from the jaws of many violent Deaths, wherewith the Raging Waves, Forein Enemies, and accurſed Domeſtick Traytors, have often threatned him, we are ſurely bound, even in ſubmiſſion to the unerring judgment of God, to conclude him worthy of a great Veneration, who hath all his life long evidently been the peculiar Care of Heaven. And yet this is not all; For, If we conſider him farther in reſpect unto theſe his Kingdoms, he cannot be denied to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104774:7"/> a Tender Father and Defender of them, doing what in him lieth towards the advancement of your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Abroad, making the Publick Good the Rule and Square of his Actions at Home, ſuffering his own Reſt and Quiet to be frequently interrupted for the ſake of other mens Security, condeſcending in many inſtances, even beneath the Grandeur of his Royal Station, in order to the ſatisfaction of his people, and in a word, ſo managing his Actions in the general courſe of them, as is moſt likely effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to render himſelf one of the moſt Glorious of Princes, and us abſolutely the moſt happy People in the world. And are we not then even in Honor bound to Honor ſuch a Prince? But,</p>
            <p>3. If there be any here preſent, who are not to be prevailed on either by this or the fore-mentioned Obligation, let them moreover conſider that they are obliged unto the ſame by the dictates of common Prudence. For, when all is done, even in reſpect of this Life, Loyalty is ordinarily the beſt Policy; and tho it be true indeed that there are ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar examples to be produced, of Honeſt men who have been utterly ruined for their Fidelity to their King, and of Villans who have raiſed themſelves plentiful Fortunes by their oppoſition to him; yet generally ſpeaking, or for the moſt part, the beſt and moſt likely way of being good and kind to our ſelves in our Temporal, as well as Spiritual, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104774:7"/> is to be juſt and faithful unto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> If you look back to the Hiſtory of the late times of Anarchy and Confuſion, you will there indeed obſerve Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion for a while very Triumphant and Proſperous; he that was the leaſt troubled with a bogling Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that could audaciouſly attempt the moſt Sawcy and Virulent things againſt Royal Majeſty, put himſelf in the faireſt way for a publick vogue, and for that which is uſually conſequent thereunto, the capacity of ſoon getting a great Eſtate. But if you likewiſe remark the Iſſues of things, pray what generally became of thoſe Impudent Hotſpurs at a long run? Many of them you will find were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done and deſtroyed by others of their own Faction; and tho ſome others had a long time the good luck to ſecure themſelves, notwithſtanding all the various changes and viciſſitude of affairs, yet Divine Juſtice hath already overtaken the far greateſt part of them, the Perſons of ſome being brought to tragical and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable ends, and the Eſtates of the moſt being come to nought, their Families impoveriſhed, and ſcarce any thing of them remaining behind, beſides their Names, to be deteſted and abhorred by all ſucceeding Generations. Nay farther yet, if we reflect on the Tranſactions that have occurred within the compaſs of theſe few years, what is it that the Hot-headed Bigots of the Faction have got by all their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed Plots and Conſpiracies? Have they indeed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104774:8"/> the propoſed ends of increaſing their Wealth, and ſwelling their Titles, and of living more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily and joyfully than they did before? It muſt be confeſſed that at one time they grew very rampant and domineering, and ſeemed too too likely by their number and noiſe to bear down all before them. But when the Meaſure of their Arbitrary and Seditious Practices was once filled up, God was then pleaſed to make even thoſe very Practices the Inſtruments of their ruin, and inſtead of bleſſing them with the expected ſucceſs, miraculouſly to blaſt and confound all their devices; ſo that now they are become in all their capacities Fatal Examples of the miſchiefs ariſing from Diſloyalty, and we may boldly with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſay of them and of all villanous<note place="margin">Pſal. lxxiii. 18.</note> undertakings, O how ſuddenly do they conſume, periſh, and come to a fearful end!</p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavoured to repreſent unto you, what great obligations there are lying on all Subjects to <hi>Honor the King.</hi> I come now in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place to ſhew you, what are the moſt proper and effectual methods for the Honor by. And thoſe that I ſhall at preſent diſcourſe of, and which are indeed the chiefeſt, ſhall be the three that follow, <hi>viz.</hi> We are obliged to expreſs our Honor of the King,</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104774:8"/>
               <item>I. By always ſpeaking reſpectfully of his Perſon;</item>
               <item>II. By yielding a due obedience unto his Laws;</item>
               <item>III. By endeavouring the promotion of his other juſt Intereſts on all emergent occaſions, tho we be not by the letter of any Human Statute compellible thereunto.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. By always ſpeaking reſpectfully of his Perſon. And this indeed (tho it be one of the meaneſt and loweſt manifeſtations of our duty, yet) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in it ſelf ſo indiſpenſable, as that I know not how we can rightly be denominated ſo much as Chriſtians, if we cuſtomarily act in contradiction to it. For ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely tender is our Holy Religion of the Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all men, as that it by no means permits us to ſpeak evil of any, even the moſt inferior perſon: nay we are not only forbid to detract from ſuch an one, by inventing or ſpreading a falſe report, but even by unneceſſarily relating an Uncharitable Truth, concerning him. And how much leſs then doth our Religion permit us to ſpeak evil of Gods Anointed, whom he hath deputed to Reign in his own ſtead? <hi>St. Jude</hi> tells us in the ninth verſe of his Epiſtle, that <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel durſt not bring a railing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation even againſt the Devil himſelf: for tho he be only an accurſed Prince of the Air, yet becauſe he is a Prince, a favourable modeſty of ſpeech towards him was adjudged beſt becoming. And if ſo, then ſurely they have great reaſon with ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104774:9"/> of Face to reflect upon themſelves; who think it not enough formerly to have been concerned in the moſt damnably malicious defamations of their Sovereign Liege Lord, but ſtill perſevere in the making it a part of their Saintſhip to vilifie and traduce him, ſometimes by unjuſt and unreaſonable inſinuations, and more often by groundleſs forgeries and lyes. But (beloved) we have not ſo learnt Chriſt, the Rules of our Profeſſion requiring of us a directly contrary behaviour; and therefore, if we would act agreeably to the Injunctions thereof, it is neceſſary for us, in caſe we ever hear of any Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, wherewith the King as a man is encompaſſed (and who alas! Is there that can plead an exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from ſuch?) preſently to cover them with the Mantle of Piety and Charity, perfectly abominating any the leaſt reſemblance to the inhuman crime of * <hi>Ham,</hi> when he delighted to gaze<note place="margin">Gen. i. 22.</note> upon and publiſh his Fathers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But this is not all, for we are in like manner ſtrictly bound to take all convenient opportunities of diſplaying the many Admirable accompliſhments and endowments, which render the King deſervedly Illuſtrious, not only forbearing to ſpeak ill, but ſpeaking as well of him as we may and ought; that his Enemies may be the more aſhamed of their baſe and unjuſtifiable Diſobedience, and his Friends the more readily excited to the engaging themſelves in.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104774:9"/> his Services, even tho they were ſure of becoming Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices thereby. But,</p>
            <p>2. Beſides the ſpeaking reſpectfully of him, if we would indeed Honor him aright, we muſt likewiſe yield a due obedience unto his Laws, thoſe I mean which are ſtill in force, and ſo far as they are in force. For as our Saviour hath made the obſervation of his Laws the Teſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſtinguiſh his Friends from his Enemies (<note n="*" place="margin">John xv. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are my friends,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if ye do whatſoever I command you:</hi>) So the ſame may be proportionably ſaid of the obſervation of the Kings Laws too. But among the reſt there are three ſorts of them more eſpecially, which exact a thorough conformity from all thoſe, who would in good earneſt be thought to deſerve the reputable Character of the Kings Friends, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Thoſe which concern Uniformity in Divine Worſhip; 2. Thoſe which prohibit the Levying of Arms againſt the King upon any pretence whatſoever; 3. Thoſe which determine the payment of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe which concern Uniformity, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable experience hath all along demonſtrated, how abſolutely neceſſary that is for the ſupport of the Crown; Recuſants of all ſorts having ever ſince the Reformation been the Inſtruments of almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſturbances in the State; and it being more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104774:10"/> eſpecially obſervable of our Fanatick Recuſants, that notwithſtanding all the noiſes, which they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made concerning their own godlineſs and their good meanings, yet (to ſpeak within compaſs) there was in all probability not one in five hundred of them, but what evidently enough appeared at leaſt to have wiſhed well to the ſucceſs of the late Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Arms. And therefore, if we would not be thought Confederates with thoſe, who every day undermine the True Intereſts of the Crown and the preſent Government, one of the moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual methods is intimately to adhere to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Eſtabliſhed Church, than which none can poſſibly be more Loyal in the world.</p>
            <p>And ſo again as to thoſe Laws which prohibit the Levying of Arms againſt the King, altho there have been ſome indeed, who have been impudent enough to aſſert, that the ſo doing is conſiſtent with the Duty of a good Subject, declaring even when they were in actual Rebellion againſt their Sovereign, that they intended nothing elſe thereby but only to make him a moſt Glorious Prince, yet the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious abſurdity of this Paradox was notoriouſly interpreted by the terrible event, the Glory (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly) deſigned, being not that of a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Throne here, but the Glory of dying a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred Sacrifice to the implacable fury of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Which kind of Glory, tho I queſtion not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104774:10"/> but that in the conſequence of it proved infinitely happy to that Ever-Bleſſed Saint, yet God forbid that it ſhould ever be made a Preſident of a way to Honor the King in future Ages! For ſurely it is a very ſtrange expreſſion of Honor inhumanly to murther the perſon Honored; nay to do any thing in the leaſt meaſure tending thereunto, muſt needs be directly repugnant to the duties of Fidelity and Obedience.</p>
            <p>And ſo laſtly as to thoſe Laws which determine the payment of Tribute, it is plain that thereby a Legal Right unto thoſe ſums of mony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpecified, whether they be greater or leſs, is devolved upon the King; and tho it is to be feared, that there are too many in the Kingdom, who take all the ſecret opportunities of defrauding him thereof, and that notwithſtanding ſtill reckon themſelves Mighty Loyalliſts, yet for my part I muſt confeſs that I am not able to reconcile things ſo very oppoſite and contradictory. Our Saviour I am ſure manifeſted his own Loyalty, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to manifeſt ours, <note n="*" place="margin">Mark xii. 17.</note> by giving unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars:</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> among other inſtances of ſubjection injoyns this as one, <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. xiii. 7.</note> that we ſhould render Tribute to whom Tribute is due; Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom. From whence it clearly follows, unleſs we will deny our Saviour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104774:11"/> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> to have been competent Judges of the Obligations of Loyalty, that he that cheateth the King of his Cuſtom, or any other Dues, is in ſo doing an evil and a diſobedient Subject, neither truly Loyal, nor Chriſtian. But,</p>
            <p>3. It is not ſufficient for us, if we would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Honor the King aright, to ſpeak reſpectfully of him, and to be obedient to his expreſs Laws, it being likewiſe required of us to endeavour the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of all his other Juſt Intereſts on all emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſions, tho we be not by the Letter of any Human Statute compellible thereunto. For ſuch a defect of knowledge always attends all Human Legiſlators, as that it is utterly impoſſible for them to foreſee the various accidents that contingently ariſe, and therefore they cannot in many particular caſes explicitly preſcribe what is neceſſary to be done in order to the Publick Good. From whence it cometh to paſs that in many weighty tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which have a great influence upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, men are left indeterminately on the one ſide or the other to act according to the Liberty of their own Wills; inſomuch that it is eaſily poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man to come up to the Letter of thoſe Eſtabliſhed Laws, which uſually fall under cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, and yet at the ſame time to be a very ill and pernicious Member of Society. Thus, for example, in the Popular Election of Officers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104774:11"/> to Publick Truſts and Employs, the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Kingdom certainly require us only to Vote for thoſe, who by the ſoundneſs of their Principles, and other neceſſary qualifications, are well capacitated for the reſpective Places, for which they are Candidates. But yet, becauſe it is not poſſible for the Law-giver upon all occaſions to determine, what perſons are well capacitated, and what not, therefore the liberty of determining that is thought fit for ſome Political reaſons to be indulged to the People. Which liberty not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding if any man ſo far abuſeth, as to throw away his Voice upon a Perſon known to be Diſtaffected to the Government, or otherwiſe unqualified, let him call himſelf as good a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Kings-man as he pleaſeth, yet in this at leaſt he acteth contrarily to the duties of ſuch. And as it is not allowable for any man to abuſe the Liberty granted him to the Kings Diſſervice in this Caſe, ſo neither is it in any other Parallel Caſe that doth occur. Concerning which point it is farther to be obſerved, that tho abuſes of this kind are not properly and in themſelves pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the Laws of the Land, yet they cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly render us obnoxious to the Laws of God, he having indefinitely commanded us to do what in us lieth for the advancement of the Kings Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104774:12"/> and we therefore being unavoidably obliged thereunto in all manner of Inſtances, excepting only thoſe which interfere with ſome ſuperior Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, that clearly appeareth to be his Command.</p>
            <p>And thus I have diſpatched the ſecond Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral propoſed, and come now in the third place to repreſent, how unreaſonably ſome men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Honor the King, when their Practices run counter to his Intereſts. Such more particularly I mean,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Who only talk for the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and never act any thing;</item>
               <item>II. Who tho they Act ſomtimes well, yet are often biaſſed by ſiniſter reſpects and conſiderations to the acting ill;</item>
               <item>III. And laſtly, Who lead debauched and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lives.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. Who only talk for the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and never Act any thing. And theſe indeed are a dangerous ſort of Plauſible Hypocrites, who uſually do as much prejudice to the Kings Cauſe, as his moſt avowed Enemies. Nay ſometimes they do much more; for, whereas his avowed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are always ſuſpected, and therefore narrowly watched, and ſeldom or never truſted in any thing, theſe men, before they are well known, too often
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104774:12"/> occaſion ſome degree of confidence to be repoſed in them, and by that means cunningly ſlip into Publick Offices, anſwerable to their reſpective qualities. But when they have ſo done, then they begin to ſhew themſelves by deceiving the expectations that were conceived of them; for, inſtead of being really inſtrumental in the ſervice of the Crown, their time is chiefly ſpent in conſulting their own eaſe and quiet, thinking it enough to enjoy the Honor, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out undergoing any thing of the Burthen, of the Places to which they are called. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an immoderate deſire of Pleaſure, and hatred of buſineſs ſeduce them from their Duty; either their Luſts prevail upon them to play the Wantons, or the Good-Fellows, or to proſecute ſome diverting Sports or Games, and therefore they cannot be at leiſure when there is need of them. Othertimes through Cowardiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant Fear they quit the exerciſe of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Authority together; if they ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in ſuch and ſuch difficult points, they are afraid it may be the worſe for them hereafter, and therefore they are reſolved to ſleep in a whole Skin, and to have nothing to do in thoſe matters. Othertimes again a covetous principle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104774:13"/> operates within them, and ſuggeſteth great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that may accrue, if they will be but abſent at ſuch a time; mony perhaps may be gotten abroad, or ſaved at home, Relations may be gratified, or obligations may be laid upon ſome who may do good turns another way, and therefore they pretend that they have ſome private concerns that are not to be diſpenſed with, and ſo excuſe themſelves. And thus by the prevalence of theſe and ſuch like temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when any buſineſs of real importance is to be done, they conſtantly ſlip their Necks out of the Collar, leaving the King to ſhift for himſelf as well as he can, and preferring their own corrupt affections and ſenſual intereſts to the common Good. And are not ſuch perſons then, if they call themſelves Loyaliſts, Ufurpers of that Honorable Name? Yes certainly; for, if they had any real Title thereunto, they would at leaſt be ſo far Maſters of themſelves, as to control and over-rule thoſe their vicious Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, when they ariſe in oppoſition to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duties of their Station, and the Publick advantage. But,</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104774:13"/>
            <p>2. Thoſe men likewiſe unreaſonably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Honor the King, as they ought to do, who, tho they Act ſometimes well, yet are often biaſſed by ſiniſter reſpects and conſiderations to the acting ill. For he that truly and really honoreth the King, doth it uniformly and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, as well in one inſtance as another; he is not at any time to be induced either with <hi>Judas,</hi> or the Rebel <hi>Scots</hi> to ſell his Maſter for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but is conſtantly honeſt and juſt unto him, even tho he were ſure of loſing, as well as tho he were likely of getting, an Eſtate by ſerving him. If therefore any man cometh to bargain with him for the doing any thing contrary to the Intereſts of his Prince and Country, he flieth from him as from a Poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Serpent; he deteſteth the perſon, who durſt affront him ſo groſly, as to think him ſo baſe and mercenary a Traytor; and he abominateth the offered reward of unrighteouſneſs with the ſame kind of Holy Indignation, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did, when in the zeal of his ſoul he ſaid unto <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts viii. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Thy mony periſh with thee!</hi> Which generous diſpoſition is indeed implanted in the very Habit of his mind;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104774:14"/> for he is Loyal upon Principles, and for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake; not for the hopes of preferment, not by chance or good fortune, not becauſe it is Faſhionable to be ſo; but becauſe God hath poſitively required it of him, and hath made it one ſpecial part of his Unchangeable Law. Whereas now, if on the other ſide we review the perſons of whom we were ſpeaking, it is ſtrange to obſerve into how many Shapes mony is able to change them. Sometimes there are no men ſo high for Conformity and Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as they, and (if you will believe them) they would not by their good wills leave a Wealthy Fanatick, and much leſs a Rebel, in <hi>England.</hi> Othertimes they Advocate for pity to be ſhewn to ſuch a man whom they name, for that, tho he hath juſtly incurred the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Recuſancy, or it may be forfeited his life, yet by favor and fair means he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be made a Proſelyte. And ſo in many other particulars very eaſie to be reckoned up, were it neceſſary, they claſh and interfere with themſelves; the true reaſon of which is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their pretended Loyalty is not bottomed upon the firm Foundation of Religion, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things variable and uncertain, I mean their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104774:14"/> own advantages. And what praiſe then is really unto ſuch perſons? Upon what account can the King be really ſaid to be beholden to them? For though they be ſuppoſed ſometime to perform Services, if conſidered in themſelves, ſignal and Eminent, yet when they perform them for their own ſakes, and not for the ſake of the King, as our Saviour <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. vi. 2.</note> ſaith in another caſe, <hi>Verily they have their reward.</hi> But then moreover, when they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves demonſtrate by their actions, that the very ſame principle, which leads them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be Serviceable to the Crown, can othertimes lead them to be Diſſerviceable to the ſame, they have no reaſon to boaſt that they deſerve to receive Honor from it, when they really ſhew none at all to it. But,</p>
            <p>3. And laſtly, Thoſe men in like manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably pretend to Honor the King in the full ſenſe and meaning of the Text, who lead debauched and irregular lives. For tho ſuch perſons indeed may chearfully embark them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Kings Buſineſs, and heartily wiſh well to his Cauſe, and ſometimes in their ſeveral Spheres do brave and acceptable things, yet by their groſs and ſcandalous Immoralities they cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104774:15"/> countermine themſelves, and mightily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number and ſtrength of the Party which they ſay they hate. For although it be in it ſelf highly abſurd and unreaſonable, for any men to encourage themſelves in Diſloyalty againſt their Prince, becauſe there are ſome on their Princes ſide, who are Diſloyal to their Maker, eſpecially conſidering how obnoxious the Oppoſite Party is to much more ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminations; yet <hi>de facto</hi> we find that the open impieties of ſome, who call themſelves Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alliſts, are frequently made an argument againſt Loyalty it ſelf, and that that Argument is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally adjudged very cogent and demonſtrative by the common and injudicious ſort of people: and ſo it comes to paſs that the King loſes the hearts of many of his Subjects, who are by theſe means decoyed out of their Duty and Allegiance, even to the Aſſociating themſelves with his profeſſed Adverſaries. But this is not the only miſchief which the vicious and Immoral behaviour of ſuch perſons doth; for it is more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſadly obſervable, that thereby they do what in them lieth, tho inconſiderately perhaps and beſides their intentions, for the bringing down the heavy wrath of God, not only on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104774:15"/> themſelves, but on their Sovereign too. To which purpoſe it is remarkable, when <hi>Samuel</hi> exhorteth the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to fear the Lord, and to ſerve him in Truth with all their heart (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> xii. 24.) that one great Motive which he uſeth with them is this, that if they ſtill did wickedly, they ſhould be conſumed, both they and their King. The Juſtice of which threatning, if it be called in queſtion, may be cleared from hence, that the proper way of taking vengeance upon Kingdoms for a General and National wickedneſs, is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting a General and National puniſhment, which can never be done, but that the King, who is the Head of the Body Politick, muſt needs bear a large ſhare in it, in proportion to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality of that which the Body beareth. So that from hence it follows, that every wicked man, as he is a wicked man, is a real Enemy to his Prince, becauſe as ſuch, he for one contributes to the provoking and incenſing God unto the exerciſe of his fury, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying both Prince and People by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fate. And therefore they, who would in good earneſt promote and perpetuate the Honor of their Prince, are ſtrictly bound, if they will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104774:16"/> not live religiouſly for Gods ſake, or their own, yet at leaſt to live ſo for the ſake of their Prince, whoſe ſafety and happineſs ſo much depend upon the piety and vertue of his People.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with the three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Heads of diſcourſe propoſed to be ſpoken to. From all which it cannot but appear, that in order to the Conſtituting and Making a truly Loyal man a great many things are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely required, and that not every one who Honoreth the King in ſome few Caſes, but he alone who Honoreth him in all, hath a juſt claim to that Appellation. And if ſo, then let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade and prevail upon all here preſent, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon you who are the Great and Flouriſhing Hopes of this City, not to content your ſelves with a formal and ſuperficial appearance of Loyalty, but conſtantly to endeavour in your reſpective Stations the manifeſtation of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward power and virtue thereof. You have lately given to your ſelves a Gallant and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Preſident of ſo doing; for no more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of you, but only to continue Acting conſiſtently and agreeably to what you did the other day, when you ſo eagerly courted the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of being in Arms againſt the Rebels.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104774:16"/> Do but ſtill perſevere in diſvaluing all your other private Intereſts, when the King's are at ſtake, as you then ſeemed to diſvalue your very lives, and you cannot fail of performing the Whole of this Duty. For your farther encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement whereunto you would do well to conſider, that you have now the Honor of being Headed by <note n="*" place="margin">The Right Honorablethe Lord <hi>Arthur Somerſet.</hi>
               </note> a Truly No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Right Honorable Leader, a Leader, whoſe example, if you attend to it, may be a Living Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Loyalty; and therefore, ſeeing you have voluntarily liſted yourſelves under ſo Great a Command, it will be the baſeſt thing in the world, if hereafter you ſhould diſgrace both his Lordſhip and your ſelves by turning Renega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does or Apoſtates. But this is not the only bond wherewith you are obliged; for you may likewiſe reflect on the Solemnity of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Addreſſes, which together with your ſelves you have been admitted to proſtrate at the King's feet; and conſequently you cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a monſtrous vileneſs and diſingenuity violate thoſe Promiſes, which you have ſo ſacredly and frequently made. But above all it will be proper for you to remember, that your Eternal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104774:17"/> Salvation very much depends upon the diſcharge of this Duty of Obedience the right way; and therefore, if you have any regard to your own well-being hereafter, let this conſideration like wiſe be inſtrumental in nouriſhing and increaſing your Fervent Zeal; that ſo at the laſt day, when the Great King of Heaven comes to make a Scrutiny into your Actions, and inquireth eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w you have behaved your ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Vice-Gerents on Earth, you may be found in the number of thoſe, who ſhall be counted worthy to Rule, becauſe they have not thought it any ways unworthy of them to Obey, and may be exalted to thoſe everlaſting Thrones of Glory and Happineſs, where all the moſt tranſporting ſatisfactions of infinite Splendor and Triumph are to be enjoyed. Which God grant even for the merits of his Bleſſed Son! <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
